Welcome to the first R tutorial video,
where we'll go over some of the basics of working
with the programming language R. The video will provide
a general orientation to the RStudio workspace,
how to set up your working directory, how to import a data
set and provide a few tips for coding in R.
So if you've never used R before,
this should be a helpful place to start.
So let's start by looking at the four different windows
inside the RStudio workspace.
In the bottom-left window is the console.
This is like the command prompt window,
where you can enter commands to tell R to do something.
For example, I can enter a math command like 2 + 2, hit Enter,
and I get back a single element of output, in this case, 4.
I could also enter rep 1, comma, 100, inside brackets,
hit Enter, and this time, R gives me back
a vector of length 100, which is just 1 repeated 100 times.
On the top-left window is what we call the R script.
This is like a scratch pad where you
can write your commands without actually
having to run them right away.
This is nice, because you can save your progress on a script
and pick up later where you left off.
As you can see, I premade a script here,
which contains a few commands that we'll
go over in this video.
So if you have a line of code in the script,
you can execute this command directly.
Just move your cursor to the script line,
and then click on the Run button.
You can also select multiple lines of code
and run them at once.
Alternatively, I could just click the code that I want
and hit Control-R to run the command.
If I want to save my script, I can just
go to the File dropdown menu and click on Save.
On the upper-right window, we normally
see what's called the environment.
This window tells us all the various data sets, functions,
or other objects that are currently in your work session.
For example, we could create a sequence of numbers
from 0 to 50 by intervals of 2 and store
this as a vector object.
We can see our new vector just by entering
the name of the object, and we see
it appear in the top-right environment window.
Finally, in the bottom right, there's
a miscellaneous window that usually displays
any visual outputs that come from our commands
or show us help files.
For example, I can create a very simple visual output
by plotting my_object, the string of numbers
that I just created.
To do this, I'll just enter plot(my_object) and run
this code, and we see that R makes
a nice little graphic for us and displays it
in the bottom-right window
OK, so now that we have some basic orientation
around the RStudio workspace, one of the first things
you'll always want to do after opening our
is make sure that you're working in
the correct working directory.
The working directory is basically
the location on your computer where
R is looking while you're running the program.
If you tell R to load any files or data sets,
you can only do this if you tell R where to look.
Similarly, if you save something in R,
like a script or a graphic, it will normally
be saved to the current working directory.
So to find out what my current working directory is,
I can enter getwd with curly brackets
and run this line of code.
In the console, we can see that the output
is a file pathway to the current working directory.
If I'm happy working from this folder,
I can just leave this alone and move on.
But if I want to change my working directory,
then I can use the command setwd and enter the new file
pathway inside the brackets.
One note about changing your working directory--
always make sure that the slashes in your file pathway
are going forward.
Also, that the pathway is inside quotation marks.
Sometimes, if you copy and paste a file pathway name
from somewhere else, the slashes might be the wrong way,
and R will not be happy.
For example, in this file pathway,
my slashes are going the wrong way.
And if I tried to run this, I get an error message.
So now that you've loaded up R and gotten your working
directory sorted out, the next thing you might want to do
is load some data.
There are a lot of different types
of data that R can load for you, including files normally used
in other data analysis programs like Excel, Stata, or SPSS.
Sometimes depending on the version of our
that you're working with you might
have to load a specific package in R that will allow you
to read the data more easily.
Packages are basically bundles of commands or code
that people have made that allow R to do various tasks more
easily.
R comes with a standard set of packages,
but sometimes you'll need to install new packages, depending
what you're trying to do.
You can always use Google searches
to figure out which package you need for the task at hand.
So let's start with two common types
of data sets, Excel files and CSV, or Comma-Separated Value
files.
If I know that the data set I want to load is saved
as an Excel spreadsheet, I can read this data set directly
into R using the readxl package. .
So first I'll enter the command install_packages, and then
type readxl inside the quotation marks.
After running this, the package will
be downloaded and installed, and then I
can use the library command to load the package in R.
So now I'm ready to load my Excel data set.
So now, in this next line of code,
I'm using the command read_excel to read in the data set.
The arrow here is assigning this data
set to a new object in the workspace,
and the object is called my_exceldata.
So running this code, I see that my data set appears
in the environment window.
I can now click on this to look at it
and see that my data set has loaded correctly.
So I see that my data set of just two variables and three
observations has loaded correctly.
Now, another way to load data in R
is to click on Import Data Set, and then
select From Text File--
or sometimes, this might appear as From Excel or From CSV.
So loading CSV files is similar.
This time, I'll use the read_csv command to read in my data.
So we see that a new data set appears.
I can click on it once again and see now,
I've loaded a second data set, this one with three variables.
Other types of data sets you might encounter include .dta
files which are commonly used in Stata, and .sav files,
which are commonly used in SPSS.
So when loading a .dta file for the first time,
you'll need to install and load the package Foreign.
And once this has been installed and loaded successfully,
you can load the DTA file using a similar script as before.
So I see that my DTA file has loaded.
I can click on it to view the data set.
And similarly, with .sav files, I'll need to install and load
the package Haven.
And then I can read in my SPSS data.
Click on it once again, wait for it to load,
and I see that my data set's loaded successfully.
OK, so hopefully now, you're ready to get started
working with your data in R. To conclude a video,
let's go over a few final tips that
can improve your R experience.
So first, remember that R is very picky about punctuation.
Always check your brackets and commas in your code
if you're getting errors.
Remember, we generally use round brackets
to specify arguments inside a command,
while we use square brackets to specify the location
inside a data object.
For example, I could open up the square brackets
and put 1 inside here, and this would tell me the first element
of the vector of my object.
If I have a 2 inside the square block brackets,
it'll tell me the second element.
And if I have a 3, it'll give me the third element.
Second, always try to comment your code and label
things in a logical way.
That way, both you and others can understand
what your code is doing.
For example, in the script I've just created,
I'm using these pound characters to create
comment code that explains each piece of my script.
Finally, when you use a new command or a function
for the first time, something that's helpful to do
is to check out the help file and try a working example
so that you understand what the code is doing.
For example, to see the help file for the sample command,
I can just type ?sample and run this.
So this loads the help file for the sample command,
and I can read through this documentation
to see which arguments go into it.
And if I scroll down to the bottom,
there's code for some working examples.
So if we copied and pasted the code for 100 Bernoulli
trials, which I have here, we can
see that this code delivers 100 elements of either 0 or 1.